Guide to the Yale University Press Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Yale University Press records
1919-1964
YCAL MSS 552
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.09
(23 boxes)
The records contain setting copies and proofs for works published by the press from 1919 through 1964 for many well-known twentieth century authors. Materials relating to multiple titles dating from the 1950s can be found, for example, for Gertrude Stein and Eugene O'Neill. Works can also be found for a number of authors affiliated with the University either as students or faculty. Many of the early titles in the collection were published as part of the Yale Series of Younger Poets. These authors include: Alfred Bellinger, the publisher John Chipman Farrar, John Hollander, Victor Starbuck, Viola Chittenden White, Amos Niven Wilder, and Wayland Wells Williams.
Yale University Press
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Yale University Press, 1926-1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Yale University Press Records (RU 554). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Yale University Press
See "A Brief History of Yale University Press" by Robert Pranzatelli, adapted from A World of Letters by Nicholas A. Basbanes, available at <http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/about.asp>.
Scope and Contents
The Yale University Press records contain setting copies and proofs for works published by the press from 1919 through 1964 for many well-known twentieth century authors. Materials relating to multiple titles dating from the 1950s can be found, for example, for Gertrude Stein and Eugene O'Neill. Works can also be found for a number of authors affiliated with the University either as students or faculty. Many of the early titles in the collection were published as part of the Yale Series of Younger Poets. These authors include: Alfred Bellinger, the publisher John Chipman Farrar, John Hollander, Victor Starbuck, Viola Chittenden White, Amos Niven Wilder, and Wayland Wells Williams.
Most setting copies are heavily marked and annotated and in some cases setting copies, galley proofs, and page proofs are present for individual works, providing a record of the evolution of the text through the publication process.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by author and then by title for authors with more than one title to their name.
Yale series of younger poets; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors and publishers; Publishers and publishing -- Archives; University presses; Bellinger, Alfred R. (Alfred Raymond), 1893-1978; Farrar, John Chipman, 1896-1974; Hollander, John, 1929-2013; O'Neill, Eugene, 1888-1953; Starbuck, Victor; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; White, Viola C., 1890-1977; Wilder, Amos N. (Amos Niven), 1895-1993; Williams, Wayland Wells, 1888-1945; Yale University Press
- Publications
  - Bellinger, Alfred R. (Alfred Raymond)
    - Spires and Poplars, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Berenson, Bernard
    - Studies in Medieval Painting, [circa 1921]-1930; 5 (Box 1)
  - Brombert, Victor
    - The Criticism of T. S. Eliot, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Buck, Howard Swazey
    - The Tempering, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Butler, Charles Edward
    - Cut Is the Branch, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Carter, Ernest and Brian Hooker
    - The White Bird, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Clapp, Frederick Mortimer
    - Jacopo Carucci da Pontormo, undated; 4 (Box 2)
  - Coffin, Robert P. Tristram (Robert Peter Tristam)
    - Book of Crown and Cottages, 1925 (Box 2)
  - Day, Richard Edwin
    - Dante: A Sonnet Sequence and Other Poems, 1924 (Box 3)
  - DeForest, John William
    - A Union Officer in the Reconstruction, 1947-1948; 2 (Box 3)
  - Dewey, John
    - A Common Faith, [1934] (Box 3)
  - Farrar, John Chipman
    - Forgotten Shrines, 1919 (Box 3)
    - Songs for Parents, 1921 (Box 3)
  - Fenton, Charles A.
    - "The Writer as Professor", [1960] (Box 22)
  - Ferril, Thomas Hornsby
    - Westering, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Frost, Frances M.
    - Hemlock Wall, 1929 (Box 3)
  - Hollander, John
    - A Crackling of Thorns, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Horan, Robert
    - A Beginning, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
  - Lewis, Charlton Miner
    - Poems, 1924 (Box 4)
  - Lyman, Dean Belden
    - The Last Lutanist and Other Poems, 1923 (Box 4)
  - Merriam, Eve
    - Family Circle, 1946 (Box 4)
  - Merwin, W. S. (William Stanley)
    - A Mask for Janus, 1952 (Box 4)
  - O'Neill, Eugene
    - Hughie, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Long Day's Journey into Night, 1955-1956; 3 (Box 4)
    - Long Day's Journey into Night, 1955-1956; 5 (Box 5)
    - More Stately Mansions, 1964; 5 (Box 23)
    - A Touch of the Poet, 1957; 6 (Box 5)
  - Phelps, William Lyon
    - The Chronicle History of the Life and Death of King Lear, 1917; 2 (Box 6)
  - Reid, Dorothy
    - Coach into Pumpkin, 1925 (Box 6)
  - Starbuck, Victor
    - Wind in the Pines, 1923 (Box 6)
  - Steegmuller, Francis
    - The Two Lives of James Jackson Jarves, 1950-1951; 4 (Box 6)
  - Stein, Gertrude
    - Alphabets and Birthdays, 1957; 3 (Box 7)
    - As Fine As Melanctha, 1954; 3 (Box 7)
    - As Fine As Melanctha, 1954; 2 (Box 8)
    - Bee Time Vine and Other Pieces, 1953 (Box 8)
    - Bee Time Vine and Other Pieces, 1953; 3 (Box 9)
    - Four in America, 1947-1948; 3 (Box 10)
    - Mrs. Reynolds and Five Earlier Novelettes, 1952; 3 (Box 10)
    - Mrs. Reynolds and Five Earlier Novelettes, 1952 (Box 11)
    - A Novel of Thank You, 1958; 3 (Box 11)
    - A Novel of Thank You, 1958 (Box 12)
    - Painted Lace and Other Pieces, 1955; 3 (Box 12)
    - Painted Lace and Other Pieces, 1955 (Box 13)
    - Stanzas in Meditation and Other Poems, 1956; 3 (Box 13)
    - Stanzas in Meditation and Other Poems, 1956 (Box 14)
    - Two: Gertrude Stein and Her Brother, and Other Early Portraits, 1951; 2 (Box 14)
    - Two: Gertrude Stein and Her Brother, and Other Early Portraits, 1951; 2 (Box 15)
  - Stewart, Randall
    - Nathaniel Hawthorne: A Biography, 1948; 2 (Box 15)
  - Thom, Robert
    - Children of the Lady Bug, 1956 (Box 16)
  - White, Viola Chittenden
    - Horizons, 1921 (Box 16)
  - Wilder, Amos Niven
    - Arachne, 1928 (Box 16)
    - Battle-Retrospect and Other poems, 1923 (Box 16)
  - Williams, Oscar
    - The Golden Darkness: A Book of Poems, 1921 (Box 16)
  - Williams, Stanley T.
    - The Spanish Background of American Literature, 1954; 3 (Box 16)
    - The Spanish Background of American Literature, 1954; 5 (Box 17)
  - Williams, Wayland Wells
    - The Seafarers, and Other Poems, 1924 (Box 17)
  - Wright, James
    - The Green Wall, 1957
  - Oversize
    - Hughie, 1958; 4 (Box 18)
    - Long Day's Journey into Night, 1956; 8 (Box 19)
    - A Touch of the Poet, 1957 (Box 20)
    - More Stately Mansions, 1964; 5 (Box 20)
    - Long Day's Journey into Night, 1956; 6 (Box 21)
    - A Touch of the Poet, [circa 1957] (Box 21)